<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on ollyjarvis</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on ollyjarvis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 15:14:01 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>crkbd: A Better Keyboard</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/crkbd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 15:14:01 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/crkbd/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I have been interested in mechanical keyboards for a few years now. And after a couple of years of using the Keychron K14 I now wanted to start looking for something more custom. I am always trying to improve my developer experience and workflow (see my dotfiles) (arch btw) so I went looking with a general idea to find something better than a standard keyboard.
The Corne 42 The crkbd is an Open-Source keyboard based on the Helix with a 3x6 column staggered layout and 3 thumb keys.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>I have been interested in mechanical keyboards for a few years now. And after a couple of years of using the <a href="https://www.keychron.com/pages/keychron-k14-wireless-mechanical-keyboard">Keychron K14</a> I now wanted to start looking for something more custom.
I am always trying to improve my developer experience and workflow (see my <a href="https://github.com/ollyjarvis/dotfiles">dotfiles</a>) (arch btw) so I went looking with a general idea to find something better than a standard keyboard.</p>
<h2 id="the-corne-42">The Corne 42</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/foostan/crkbd">crkbd</a> is an Open-Source keyboard based on the <a href="https://github.com/MakotoKurauchi/helix">Helix</a> with a 3x6 column staggered layout and 3 thumb keys.
<img loading="lazy" src="/posts/crkbd/images/crkbd.jpg" type="" alt="crkbd"  />
The benefits of a Corne over a more traditional keyboard are:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Column stagger</strong> instead of row stagger. Row stagger exists on keyboards to match the layout of a typewriter where it allowed multiple rows stems to miss each other. This is not ideal though as my fingers at least like to move linearly and not laterally. The column stagger aims to better match the lengths of your fingers as to not cramp index fingers or over-stretch pinkies.
<img loading="lazy" src="/posts/crkbd/images/typewriter.jpg" type="" alt="typewriter"  /></li>
<li><strong>Thumb buttons</strong>. Usually we are only pressing spacebar with two of our strongest fingers (is a thumb a finger), here we can put them to better use.</li>
<li><strong>Repairability</strong>. With access to a soldering iron it should last forever.</li>
<li><strong>Flexibility</strong>. With the also Open-Source <a href="https://qmk.fm/">QMK Firmware</a> there are a lot of posibilities. I use only the layers (to reach the keys that don&rsquo;t fit) and OLED functions but there are many more. And if you can code then you can write your own.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-layout">My Layout</h2>
<p><a href="https://github.com/ollyjarvis/qmk_firmware_corne">My QMK Fork</a></p>
<h3 id="colemak-mod-dh">Colemak Mod-DH</h3>
<p>So, why not QWERTY? Well, if I am going to make such a drastic change, why not make it even harder than it needs to be?
QWERTY is bad, by every metric it <strong>sucks</strong>. But most basically it puts the most used keys in english wherever it likes.</p>
<h4 id="qwerty-vs-colemak-heatmap">QWERTY vs. Colemak Heatmap</h4>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/posts/crkbd/images/qwerty-heatmap.png" type="" alt="QWERTY"  />
<img loading="lazy" src="/posts/crkbd/images/colemak-heatmap.png" type="" alt="COLEMAK"  />
I am actually using a modified <a href="https://colemakmods.github.io/mod-dh/">Colemak Mod-DH</a> and a different keyboard than the image but this demonstrates the benefit on some english sample text.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I am bad at typing on the Corne at the minute, barely able to get to 20 WPM currently (after 5 days), but I was bad on QWERTY (50 WPM) after over 10 years, I think that my new layout forcing me to touch type will mean I pass 50 WPM soon enough.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
